<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Thoughts</title>
 <link href="http://fiction.skryl.org/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://fiction.skryl.org/"/>
 <updated>2019-01-20T23:47:40+00:00</updated>
 <id>http://fiction.skryl.org</id>
 <author>
   <name>Alex Skryl</name>
   <email>aleksey.skryl@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>P53</title>
   <link href="http://fiction.skryl.org/2015/01/15/p53/"/>
   <updated>2015-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://fiction.skryl.org/2015/01/15/p53</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Jack Thompson carefully placed Roger into his cage as Patrick Hughes entered the lab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Hey Jack. Yuri missed our weekly. Any idea where he is?” asked the Director, looking concerned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“What?! He didn’t tell you?” replied Thompson, grinning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Tell me what?” inquired Hughes, reaching for a chair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“P53! It worked! It … more than worked!” said Thompson in an excited whisper.
He pulled up a chair next to Hughes, taking his time to contrive an explanation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Pat, do you know why most living things don’t live forever?” Thompson asked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hughes pondered the question for a second. “Assuming they don’t die
of disease or some unfortunate accident, it’s because they get old. Their cells
become less efficient with age, having to work just as hard only to get less
done. Current science blames it on DNA degradation, isn’t that right?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Yes! It’s a fidelity problem!” exclaimed Thompson, his eyes widening with
excitement. “With every copy, our genome’s signal to noise ratio decreases,
causing the cellular machinery to alter its behavior slightly. Over time, these
small errors accumulate, usually leading to what we perceive as aging, and on
rare occasion causing cancer and other nasties. Now, let me ask you this,”
Thompson continued, “considering how universal senescence is, why do you think
that nature hasn’t come up with a fix?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hughes sighed, getting impatient. “It’s a diminishing returns problem if I
remember correctly. Complex organisms die from predation, disease, hunger, and a
myriad of other causes, making their chances of living to old age slim to none.
There is no evolutionary pressure to extend lifespan because animals don’t die
of old age, they die from being eaten by other animals.” Hughes
reached for a pen and a piece of paper. “Look here. If the probability of some
creature dying in the span of a single day is 1/1000, then the probability of
them surviving for 20 years is (999/1000)^(365*20)=0.067%, which is negligible.
So, as long as they reach maturity and reproduce well before then, evolution
will consider them fit. No reason to fix what’s not broken. Right?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’m very impressed Dr. Hughes!” said Thompson smiling. “Anyhow, this is where
P53 comes in. It is a retroviral gene therapy that was intended to be a cancer
vaccine. It improves transcription fidelity and adds new mutation-triggered
apoptosis pathways. A few things that nature overlooked. Here’s the kicker
though, after vaccination, our simulations show no sign of DNA degradation over
millennia. That’s thousands of years, Pat!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Wait!” Hughes interrupted. “Am I to understand that the two of you
inadvertently created an immortality drug?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Roger is our first living test subject,” Thompson replied, glancing at the
white mouse on the other side of the room. “But if the simulations are accurate,
then he will outlive us all.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Who else knows about this?” Hughes asked, reaching for his phone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Olovnikov, myself, and now you,” said Thompson. “Why?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Brian?” Hughes spoke into the handset, “Code 42, lock us down plea…” before
he finished his sentence, Yuri Olovnikov walked into the room. There was fear in
the man’s eyes but it was overshadowed by righteous determination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“King of kings, Lord of lords; Who only hath immortality, dwelling in the light
which no man can approach unto…” Olovnikov mumbled, his voice trembling.
“Forgive me.” His fingers tensed into a fist and the lab was suddenly awash in a
brilliant white light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the dust from the explosion settled, a small white mouse ran out of the
rubble into the grassy underbrush nearby. He had a long life ahead of him.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Uncertainty</title>
   <link href="http://fiction.skryl.org/2014/07/11/uncertainty/"/>
   <updated>2014-07-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://fiction.skryl.org/2014/07/11/uncertainty</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;“Computer, report!” yelled the Captain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Sir, all primary systems are online but the star orientations do not match anything in my database.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“What was our entry confidence?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It was six nines, sir.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Nurbek swallowed hard, “Show me the trajectory map.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It looked like a water droplet in zero-g, slowly morphing while the computer was
busy plotting all the possible routes the ship may have taken to arrive here.
Nurbek was temporarily entranced by it’s beautiful complexity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lost in thought, he recalled the great men of the past. Men who believed in a
deterministic universe, where one could predict the future by simply knowing
enough about the present. It was an idea that was hopelessly wrong, yet
perfectly seductive, because it made men feel like they could become gods. But
much to Man’s dismay, the true gods had other plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Space has no shortcuts, he mused. Dreams of determinism died at the hands of
Quantum Mechanics and General Relativity. But would he be any less screwed if
the Universe was actually a Laplacian dream? No, it made no difference.
Determinism was still susceptible to chaos, the law of nature which was
responsible for his current snafu. Chaos is what made the long jumps effectively
unpredictable and extremely sensitive to small errors in entry calculations. He
simply made a wrong guess in a profession where bad guesses were the worst
possible offense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Six nines. Six fucking nines. He needed at least nine nines for a jump of this
magnitude. But he was in the middle of a war zone. Any longer and the ship would
have been blown to bits. Would waiting another second really have killed him? He
would never know. All he knew was, he would be looking at the familiar starscape
of the Virgo Cluster had he waited. Instead he was here. Somewhere. Nowhere, as
far as the computer was concerned. He glanced back at the rotating shape on the
screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He suddenly remembered his old physics professor running different colored
threads through a blob of silly putty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Imagine the strings are flight trajectories and the putty is our little cosmos.
Where would you need to enter the blob in order to come out with the red
string?” asked the professor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Where the red string enters,” I replied, not seeing where he was going with
this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“What if you messed up your calcs and entered at the green one next to it?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Then you would come out close to your intended destination, where the green one
does.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Right,” he said, “this is how space travel would work if space was linear. You
could make a mistake and still get to where you were going.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He mashed the putty in his hands for a few seconds, keeping the entry points of
the strings untouched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Where do the two strings exit now?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Far apart,” I said after locating the strings in question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So what would happen if you messed up your entry calcs in this case?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’d be screwed,” I responded with an air of understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Good, this is how real space travel works. Except the strings are
infinitesimally thin, and your room for error is almost non-existent. The lesson
here is, get your calcs right, always! And then maybe well get to have this
conversation again some day.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nurbek snapped back to reality, finally gathering the courage to ask the
lingering question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Computer, based on your survey of the cluster, will we make it out of here
alive?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The computer paused for a few seconds, as if to heighten the suspense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Unlikely, sir, but I could never be certain.”&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Sight</title>
   <link href="http://fiction.skryl.org/2013/01/11/sight/"/>
   <updated>2013-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://fiction.skryl.org/2013/01/11/sight</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It was Veleriy Zyvotov’s work that finally brought an end to the AI winter. The
Z-papers, as they became known, were a tour de force in cortical theory and
marked the beginnings of the Brain Decade. For the next dozen or so years
scientists would scrutinize and map every nook and cranny of the human neocortex
in an attempt to emulate all of its quirks. The visual system was naturally one
of the first to be dissected and trivialized. It turned out to be fairly easy to
get a feed, an image that is, of what a person saw in their mind’s eye.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tech quickly caught up with the research and the first HoloSight came out
less than two years after the academic research. All you had to do was tuck the
thing behind your ear, remember something vivid, and poof, there it was, in
colorful holography. Problem was, most people don’t remember too well, so the
pictures often appeared fuzzy, faceless, or distorted in a myriad ways. Still,
there were a few whose memories held perfect impressions of reality and whose
imaginations could paint fiction just as clearly. They were called Seers and
they became the Beethovens and Mozarts of the modern world.  Some were
classically trained, having had to retard their vision with a wooden brush and a
pastel set, but most were simply dreamers who would have never survived the
urban rat race had they lived in the decades of past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the demand grew, Sight became bidirectional and could pump all five senses
from one person to the next. You could chain together a few or broadcast to
millions, as long as there was enough bandwidth and memory to maintain the
integrity of the feed. Virtual Worlds became a dime a dozen and many liked to
jack in and tune out. They wanted to own suburban homes and have four kids, not
live in Megablocks, breathe polluted air, and have to win a lottery in order to
copulate. Sight gave them the escape they dreamed of and for a while they went
back and forth between reality and utopia. They worked for food and lived for
Sight. But something strange began to happen as more and more addicts checked
out while on the wire. Some of their avatars persisted, the machines having had
enough time to reverse engineer their identities, their souls. The bodies died
but the minds kept on living. It was a welcome feature. Soon enough regular
folks began taking their own lives, some even took their families with them.
There was a suicide streak that went on for years and for the first time in
modern history the population plummeted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you know what happens when three quarters of the world’s population takes a
dirt nap? You’d think it would be a catastrophe but it actually turned out quite
alright. The religious nuts were the first to go. They called it “Heaven on
Earth” and didn’t wait long to follow their beloved ministers to an imaginary
Salvation. The oppressed, the cynical, and the power hungry went next. Everyone
now had a choice to make, and those who stuck around all had something in
common. They were motivated and ready to start over. After a while, clean water
and air stopped being a commodity and there was enough food to feed everyone.
With a universal single mindedness we began to terraform, bringing the Earth
back to the way she was when the dinosaurs roamed, blue and green, not red and
grey.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Forgotten</title>
   <link href="http://fiction.skryl.org/2012/10/31/forgotten/"/>
   <updated>2012-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://fiction.skryl.org/2012/10/31/forgotten</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It was 3am. I woke up thinking of her. I had no idea who she was but her
presence was overwhelming. Like a black hole in my subconscious she tore
away the foundations of any structured thought. All effort to escape her grasp
was futile and ended in a constellation of unfamiliar memories. Her voice, her
scent, her face… a dizzying deja vu of someone I have never met.
  The ring of the telephone broke through the silence.
  Stumbling out of bed I reached for the handset.
  “Come over”, she said in a calm, stern voice.
I remained mute, unable to shake the fog and confusion of the persistent dream.
She hung up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I waited in anticipation, still dazed by the slew of unfamiliar memories running
through my mind. The leafs began to stir as she came into view. Her dark
hair fell down to her shoulders where a black dress was struggling to hold
on to her slender body. As she walked, the wind played with her hair and her
dress waved in desperation. She resonated with the darkness. She was gorgeous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Drive,” she said, as she slid into the back seat.
I obeyed. I didn’t know the way but I felt a strange sense of familiarity
guiding me. It was as though threads of memory were being pulled out of some
cerebral abyss and weaved back into my consciousness. With every turn she
resurrected a part of me which I had long forgotten, piecing together a life I
never knew I had. The picture continued to grow clearer, until I could finally
make out our destination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She was gone. I stood in the middle of a forested road, staring at a tall pine
tree which lay across both lanes. I remembered sitting on my knees next to that
same tree, soaking wet, holding her head as she took quick shallow breaths. Her
face was covered in lacerations, glass shards protruding from her porcelain
skin, draining her of life. I couldn’t stop the bleeding but I did my best to
slow it down. Leaving her side to search for the phone meant a quick death, not
searching for it meant certain death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They said she would be OK… She died on the way to the hospital.
They said my memory would come back within a few weeks… It has been five years.
They tried to convince me of who I was… I didn’t believe them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stepped over the fallen tree. The road ahead was dark, but having her by my
side again gave me the courage to move on.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
